Introduction

MANOJ KUMAR JENA

Media has always been one of the central questions to social structure and its processes, and is integral to the social world. It mediates the social, political and economic relationships and reshapes our imagination of them. Many of the cultural commentators have often argued that ‘we’ live in a world of situated culture, and within a ‘culture of mediation’. As one of the fundamental social units, the media plays a critical role in creating, shaping, and reflecting public opinion in a democratic society, however, public opinion is the engine that keeps the wheels of democracy turning.1 In a profound sense, media/communication is one of the unique products and producers of society’s development.2

The medium, message and meaning are essential components of communication process. Marshal McLuhan argued ‘medium is the message’,3 one can move further towards the question of meaning which is central to social relations. Messages and Meanings are vital components of the social world, as Stuart Hall argues, the meaning is a social product associated with social practices, and language and symbolizations are the certain means by which meaning is produced.4 The media, in any form, whether cinema, visual, print, or theatre, are carriers of meaning and are part of social structure and functions. The study of media and communication process is dynamic, because of changing nature of message and meaning processes. For instance, semiotics sees media as associated with social meaning and as the product of the relationships constructed between the ‘signs’. The ‘sign’ is a basic unit of communication, which could be in the form of a photograph, a traffic signal, a word, a sound, an object, or a smell, whatever the culture finds significant.5 The mediated image has multiple meanings that vary from place to place, and person to person. The content created by media and the flow of information services shaped/reshaped the social terrain; it has its own time space and ideological specificity, the routine social life revolves around the media identities, media fantasies, and media constructed realities. The fundamental question in the present context is whether the media is constructing a representational reality in the form of media reality or vice-versa. Whether media is structuring or restructuring people’s sensibilities and taken for granted realities? This is indeed an ontological question. Jim Willis argues that, ‘today, what we know comes almost entirely from the news media. However, since the media gives us only a representation of reality—a kind of shadow world with varying degrees of accuracy—our behaviour and reactions may or may not be valid or consistent with what really has transpired.’6

Willis also argues that, the media sets the public agenda, and the role of the media is to mobilize public support for special interests that dominate government and society.7 There are also questions of reproduction and legitimation of dominance, and how growing technological innovation brought about more and more control of the medium, which is ideologically specific and market-driven. Media production is intrinsically interlinked with capital, in fact, global capital with hegemonic ideological base. As has been argued, in a democratic set up, the media is the foremost tool for public discourse activities, however, the existing public sphere in a democratic social space is always contested in spite of a controlled situation where few control many. Hence, it is essential to critically analyse media and marginal question which is intrinsically associated with medium, message and meaning.

Questions related to marginals are always topical in sociology and media studies. The question about marginal and mainstream needs to be appropriately addressed. The term ‘marginal’ according to the Merriam-Webster Dictionary is ‘of relating to, or situated at a margin or border, excluded from or existing outside the mainstream of society’.8 According to Collins’ dictionary, marginal can be viewed as insignificant; they are not involved in the main events or developments in society because they are poor or have no power’.9 They are socially stigmatized and vulnerable socially, economically, and politically. The question of marginal is also embedded in sociological writings. According to sociological literature, the marginal man concept relates to Robert Park’s original interests in race and ethnic relations and migration.10 Park (1928) highlighted the question of marginal man; for him, ‘the marginal man; the man who, emerging from the ghetto in which he lived in Europe, is seeking to find a place in the freer, more complex and cosmopolitan life of an American city.’11 C.A. Goldberg argues that although Park conceived the marginal man as a general social type, he closely associated the type with the Jews of the modern era. Park was a student of and strongly influenced by Simmel, he explicitly identified the marginal man with Simmel’s own notion of the stranger, the ‘classic example’ of which for Simmel ([1908] 1971:144) was ‘the history of European Jews.’12 E.V. Stonequist’s work The Marginal Man is more on the sociological analysis, as ‘it was a kind of sociological frame of reference’, he argued ‘the marginal man is a personality type that arises at a time and a place where, out of the conflict of races and cultures, new societies, new peoples, and cultures are coming into existence. The fate which condemns him to live, at the same time, in two worlds is the same which compels him to assume, in relation to the worlds in which he lives, the role of a cosmopolitan and a stranger’.13

The marginal could also be considered as a sociological category in the Indian context on the basis of complex social differentiations, based on sexuality, gender relations, physical and mental disability, caste, class, ethnicity, religion, minority, etc. The difference and distinctiveness as a social category are intersectional and intermixed with various other categories. The marginals in India, particularly women, Dalits, disabled, and various ethnic and religious minorities, are socially, politically, and economically marginalized. The communities, groups, and individuals on the basis of caste, gender, ethnicity, religion and disabilities categories are classified as marginal on the basis of their identities and social locational specificity. They are subjected to a dominant and ossified reality constructed by the upper echelons of society. Also, they are pushed towards a culture of marginalization. These marginal groups form a major chunk of the population in Indian society, which were excluded and discriminated against on the basis of their structural position. Their voice and sufferings are never adequately represented in mainstream media. They are out of the medium, message, and meaning processes. This issue is related to historical, situational, and textual contexts. The existing dominant institutional structure, values, norms, and ideologies downgrade the marginal position.

Because of its structural locations, marginals are differently segmented, and are neglected in media production process. Here, one could see through the sociological lens how they are not only adversely affected by entrenched structural inequality but also suffer by systematic social exclusionary process. The marginal groups often confront challenges on the basis of their primordial identity; most suffered are Dalits, women, and religious minorities on the basis of their predetermined differences and negation. The dominant groups control medium message and meaning in the mainstream society. On one hand, the dominant groups are idealizing and glorifying their past and foregrounding their lineage, and on the other hand, they negate the marginal because of their lineage and social locations.

The book is an attempt to explore the relationships between marginal and different forms of communication processes. Furthermore, this book tries to unravel the linkages between the media and the caste, class, gender, minority, political and ideological structures of Indian society in general.

ABOUT THE BOOK

This book attempts to highlight the role and relationship of media and marginals in India precisely in terms of gender, Dalit, disability, labour, the Sikh minority and ethnic minorities in India. The book addresses issues about the interrelationship between the communication process, the economic, political and ideological structures of Indian society, and their relationships with marginal, particularly at structural and meaning levels. It also tries to determine how the mediated phenomena have led to a shift in the discourse on marginals. It aims to present new and emerging analyses of caste, gender, and minority questions in the Indian media pertaining to structure, process, representation, production, consumption, and meaning-making process. It also tries to figure out how the mediated phenomena have brought a shift in the discourse on the question of marginal in India.

The book is intended to understand the key concerns of marginals in India, specifically with reference to women, Dalits, minorities, marginal labourers, and people with disabilities in various mediums, including cinema and theatre. The nine chapters of the book from well-known scholars in sociology, media studies, gender studies, labour studies, and linguistic studies from India and abroad, focus on several new dimensions in the Sociology and media research with a particular thrust on areas like women, Dalits, and minorities, including Sikhs and Muslims. These chapters reflect on a range of topics affecting the life of the marginals by the existing social realities, structural imbalances, violence, reinforcement of stereotypes, negations and negotiations. All the chapters illustrate conceptual and methodological questions related to the social positioning of the marginals covering empirical and theoretical aspects. The book’s strength lies in exploring the experiential narratives and lived realities of marginals. The issues of women’s agency and empowerment through cultural production, representation of gender, caste, and violence in popular culture are integral part of the book. The book provides a newer perspective on the sociology of media.

The first chapter, Gender, Sexuality and Cinema: Reinforcing the Stereotypes deals with the issue of cinema, gender and sexuality. It focuses on how violence is inherent in the actual depiction of women and mainstream media, including defining and redefining their identity. The chapter analyses the relationship between mainstream media and women, particularly how violence occurs inherent in the very depiction of women and mainstream media, as well as in defining women’s identity.

The second chapter, Hindi Cinema and Caste Question: Ideology and Reproduction of Dominance analyses Hindi cinema from a sociological vantage point, particularly Hindi cinema as an institution and art form, as well as its social, cultural and ideological role in society. The chapter tries to understand narration, image/photography, the power of visual imagery, technology and creative processes. Furthermore, it addresses the questions of ideology and the reproduction of caste domination in Hindi cinema. It argues how the cultural domination of Hindi cinema produces a subservient and passive self, contemporary cinema producing and reproducing dominant characters, normalising violence and subjugation through various representations. It is often argued that Hindi cinematic communication produces a dominant ideological pattern that negates marginal subjects. It has been observed that Hindi cinema storylines are more or less centred around upper-class/caste narratives, and reproduce a specific class and caste ideology.

The third chapter, Realities of the Marginal Worker, as reflected in the Medium of Cinema argues that, initially, cinema was a medium of entertainment. However, gradually, it became a powerful analytical tool for examining and reflecting the conditions of the marginals of the society. The marginals are the ‘Dalits’, sex workers, disadvantaged workers such as agricultural labourers, distressed marginal farmers, slum dwellers, street vendors, small artists and many others. This chapter provides an overview of the cinema industry and examines how some films reflect and narrate the realities of the existence of marginalised groups in Indian society, through some movies produced in Hindi. The purpose is to see to what extent the films narrated the existing conditions and what message the directors and producers attempted to deliver to the audience.

Chapter four, Disability in Cinema: A Case Study of Selected Hindi Films argues that cinema is an essential manner of representational medium, and is crucial in presenting various social realities on the screen. As cinema in general, and Hindi film in particular, has a large audience and a significant global reach, it is also essential to examine the nuances of its operation and appreciate its ideological implications and the hegemonic discourse of ableism within which it exists. In this context, the chapter highlights the question of disability in Hindi cinema and critically analyses the disability narrative in Hindi cinema. This chapter has studied selected contemporary Hindi Cinema to understand disability questions.

The fifth chapter, Epistemic Ashrāfiya-Morality and Urdu Theatre Public Sphere in Nineteenth-Century Bihar: Muslim Internal-Decoloniality argues that the introduction of Western-style stage theatre in nineteenth-century India emerged not only as a site to legitimise colonial power but also to contest colonial rule and ideologies. This chapter through the prism of Urdu theatre in the last quarter of the nineteenth century in the Indian province of Bihar, argues that beyond this grand binary division, the theatre also became a site to contest local caste-class-race-religion-based ideologies of domination. It examines how epistemic ashrāfiya morality that excluded shudra-dalit Muslims from knowledge production responded to the popularity of theatre and its ‘corrupting influences’; participation of ‘lowly’ women and men in theatre; threatening ashrāfiya moral authority; casteist prejudices; ashrāfiya collaboration with colonial power; marketised desire and consumption and other related issues.

The sixth chapter, Consuming and Producing Feminism through Indian Media: Analysis of Empowerment, Commodification in Culture Industry elucidates the ‘girl power’ rhetoric articulated in the popular and feminist discourses. While using the idea of commodification, this chapter demonstrates that not all ‘girl power’ rhetoric extends the desired opportunity for women to transcend individual consumption, proposing collective change in social relations. Furthermore, this chapter binds together the concepts of agency, empowerment and commodification in subsequent sections. This chapter demonstrates the fierceness of the ‘girl power’ rhetoric. With the support of empirical examples, this paper depicts the extent to which the commodified ‘girl power’ rhetoric has distorted feminist notions.

The seventh chapter, Mediations and the Body-Politic: The Problem of Representation Revisited argues how the question of representation has always been central to the analyses of media texts, especially in the context of studying images of the body. Subjecting textual configurations towards unravelling body politics in the context of analysing the ‘marginalized’ social groups remains a common way of approaching the problem of representation in contemporary media studies. This chapter takes a slight turn in its approach to the problem of representation and body politic by attempting a methodological realignment to underline the practices and effects that stem from text and its surroundings.

The eighth chapter Media, Minority Consciousness, Memory: Sikhs and 1984 addresses the question of Sikh minority and media, and what were some representations that Indian mass media constructed and popularised? How did these texts create a process of Sikh marginalisation? Why are these representations being contested most emphatically in the diaspora, and what are some components of new narratives that diasporic Sikhs are creating via digital technology? This chapter draws on a combination of methods, including content analysis of print media (English dallies), radio and television reports, commentaries from journalists and scholars, narrative analysis of 1984 websites and personal interviews with Sikhs in North America, the U.S. and Canada. This chapter also provides a critical appraisal of media imagery while highlighting the hitherto neglected Sikh point of view.

The ninth chapter Media, Social Media and the Gorkhaland Agitation in Darjeeling highlights the media and Gorkhaland agitation in Darjeeling. The chapter argues that media, primarily print capitalism, is considered an essential medium through which nationalism and collective identity were forged, but not until the advent of social media and 24×7 news channels did Gorkhaland movement receive any attention from the fourth pillar of democracy. This happened not only because of the ignorance of the region and the cause of the people by the media, but also due to the appalling situation of the media itself. Though the media plays an important role in a movement, it did not contribute anything to propagating the issues of the Gorkhaland movement at the national level. The use of social media helped the movement in taking the ground realities to people across the globe. With the help of social media, the movement gained momentum and protests and demonstrations were held not just in Darjeeling and other places in the country, but across different countries where even a handful of people from Darjeeling were residing. The use of social media in the agitation of 2017, and helping the leaders and, most importantly, the majority of the people to be legally, constitutionally and socially erudite and fight the state in their just and rightful demand of separation from the state of West Bengal.

NOTES

1. Edwin Emery, Phillip H. Ault and Warren K. Agee, Introduction to Mass Communication, Dodd, Mead & Company, 1969, New York, p. 16.

2. Siegelaub Seth and Matterlart Armand (eds.), Communication and Class struggle, Capitalism and Imperialism, IG/IMMRC, France, 1979, p.11.

3. M. McLuhan, Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man. McGraw Hill, New York, 1964.

4. Stuart Hall, ‘The Rediscovery of ‘Ideology’: Return of the Repressed Media studies’, in Culture, Society and Media, Michael Gurevitch et al. (ed.), Methuen & Co., London, 1982, p. 67.

5. Graeme Turner , Film as Social practice, Routledge, London, 1988.

6. Jim Willis, The Media Effect: How the News Influences Politics and Government, Praeger, Westport, 2007.

7. Ibid.

8 https://www.merriamwebster.com/dictionary/marginal#:~:text=2-,a,%3A%20not%20of%20central%20importance, accessed on 11 January 2024.

9 https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/marginal#:~:text=adjective,minor%20More%20Synonyms%20of%20marginal, accessed on 11 January 2024.

10. C.A. Goldberg, ‘Robert Park’s Marginal Man: The Career of a Concept in American Sociology’, Laboratorium: Russian Review of Social Research, 4(2), 2012, pp.199–217. Retrieved from https://www.soclabo.org/index.php/laboratorium/article/view/4.

11. R. Park, ‘Human Migration and the Marginal Man.’ The American Journal of Sociology, vol. XXXIII, no. 6, May 1928, pp. 881-893.

12. Goldberg, ‘Robert Park’s Marginal Man: The Career of a Concept in American Sociology’, Laboratorium: Russian Review of Social Research, 4(2), 2012, pp.199–217. Retrieved from https://www.soclabo.org/index.php/laboratorium/article/view/4.

13. Everett V Stonequist, The Marginal Man: A Study in Personality and Culture Conflict., Charles Scribner’s Sons, New York, 1937.

CHAPTER 1

Gender, Sexuality and Cinema
Reinforcing the Stereotype

RENUKA SINGH

INTRODUCTION

In 2015, a man in Australia escaped conviction on charges of stalking. Sandesh Baliga, who arrived in Australia from India three years prior, was arrested on charges of aggressively pursuing two different women—whom he made acquaintances with on separate occasions—while referring to himself as their boyfriend.1 In court, Mr. Baliga confessed that his behaviour was influenced by Bollywood movies which convinced him of the efficacy of relentless pursuit of women; the defence argued that obsession in such matters is ‘quite normal behaviour’ for Indian men.2 Acknowledging the peculiarity of the defendant’s cultural background, the Magistrate’s Court exempted him from conviction, on condition of good behaviour for the next five years. This event could be interpreted variously as a testament to the formidable influence of mass media in determining social norms and behaviour, as well as its capacity as a framework for constructing cultural stereotypes. Generalization of a deviant act—despite appropriate punishments existing—by describing it as ‘normal behaviour’ for Indian men, and the Court’s subsequent decision to sustain that argument in favour of exemption, is certainly a testament to a patriarchal substratum underlying modern jurisprudence, transcending socio-political and cultural boundaries.

However, the conviction in such obsessive and relentless pursuit of romantic gratification is not particular to any region such as India, nor is its depiction in mass media. The idea of a woman’s predisposition to succumb to the force of relentless pursuit is a ubiquitous conviction that forms much of the basis of modern sexual practices and performances of gender roles. Modes of pursuit and their varied depictions are periodically updated, revolving perpetually along the orbit of resolute male desire and a woman’s fait accompli of giving in to the same. The stubbornness of male desire and a woman’s inability (or desire) to overcome it, is understood as innate characteristics of masculine and feminine sexuality, and respectively act as boundaries for both. This natural and body-based understanding of social behaviour has neither been perpetual nor linear. Mapping the origins of social choices on a framework of gender is a practice that has a genesis, and is entwined with the evolution of a certain socio-political dispensation central to which is the concept of a self-conscious and knowing subject. Normalization of gendered discourses and gender identities routinely influence juridical decisions and punitive quantum. Conversely, such excesses get absorbed within the folds of embodied identities, as part of the law’s normalizing discourse. These discourses in turn constitute a larger vision of collective existence central to which are the requisites of confession and consent. Within this vision, violence, especially that of different forms of sexual crime and harassment, is understood variously, as the breakdown of the law’s deterrence against an individual’s natural and embodied instincts, as well as a lapse in social control. And it is within the moral contours of this vision that consent and its breach are appraised.

In contractarian and self-governing societies, mass media assumes its importance in terms of both, as a mirror of reflecting popular ideas as well as constructing and disseminating them. The scope of a particular medium is determined by the rules that govern the object of its engagement. In terms of research, Michel Foucault’s works provide a particularly well-calibrated framework to theorize the discourse between mass media and gender and sexuality. In terms of method, it implies that instead of the intent behind a certain discourse, it is the technology of the latter that is the unit of analysis. This at once relativizes agency to a certain technology of power rather than to certain biological and cultural determinisms and frees up space for more expansive mapping of gender politics.

SOCIAL BEHAVIOUR

The Industrial Revolution and the emergence of capitalism could be an ideal point of departure in constructing a genealogical understanding of the relationship between mass media and social behaviour. With the onslaught of the revolution, the state progressively assumes an inward gaze, preoccupying itself with problems on settled populations, increasingly routinized through strict discipline enforced in workhouses and factories, and generally in the course of everyday life in the nascent metropolis. The breakdown of feudalism followed by the emergence of free enterprise gave rise to new relationships of exploitation between individuals as well as, between individuals and their environment. Laws and customs, from this time on, are progressively aligned with the maintenance of this emerging relational network which simultaneously sustains the structure of civic life, while remaining at the centre of its engagements. However, the tautological nature of this emergent socio-economic order entails that its problems are also lingering. Due to the persistent nature of these problems, the concepts of degeneration and endemic serve as powerful models for explaining and dealing with them (Foucault: 2003). It also affects an inversion in terms of social security as henceforth, the logic and possibilities of both, crisis and security, are increasingly to be found within the society itself. Further, management or mitigation of these problems necessitates constant surveillance instead of zero-sum measures. A civic existence, therefore, is a constantly surveillant existence whereby the inward-gazing individual is a microcosm of the inward-gazing society. Society must be defended against itself as does the individual against its own. The responsibility of self-governance predicated upon knowledge of the self and its surroundings ensures the cultivation of a society that is both confessional and consensual. It marks the commencement of the journey of the knowing subject: a subject that is inward gazing while at the same time, responsible for and partaking in a collective and mutually consensual existence. Henceforth, it is this collective (population) that is the object of law; individual interest is displaced as the target of law, by what Foucault defines as ‘man-as-species’.3 It marks the emergence of a new form of rule—focussed upon fixing the parameters of a self-contained collective existence—which Foucault terms ‘biopolitics’.4 Thus, the knowing subject is essentially biopolitical, inducted into the process of knowing itself and its milieu from the earliest stages of its life. Public space is cultivated as a confessional space as it would constitute an important part of an individual’s learning discourse. However, neither is public space the only one for discursive learning nor is confession within this space unbridled by rules.

Public and Private Domain

The production of public-private dichotomy and characterization of the public space as liberating was achieved in no small measure by arrogating sexuality to the private domain. However, such a characterization of the public could find moral purchase only based on various confessional practices in myriad discourses of civic life. It is one’s confession of individual choices and practices of the private—expressed through various walks of public life—is what discursively integrates the public space as one of accountability, liberty and equality. Therefore, the true nature of public space derives its authority from this elementary factor of confession which in turn, derives its moral authority from the Christian concept of liberty through confession. The privation of sexuality, however, posed a problem for exhaustive confession in public discourse. Specifically, confession or expression of sexual matters had to bypass the prohibitions of bourgeois etiquette, yet be expressive enough to be considered as true. This was important because not only were the sexual practices and choices of the population increasingly becoming a core concern for the modern state, but because the very practices of expression and confession were instrumental in constituting certain discursive mechanisms and institutions that would assume authority in matters of determining meaning in modernity.

Rules of etiquette, decreeing a code of silence around sexuality and sexual matters in public discourse, and sourced out of old ascetic views of treating the body as an adversary, compelled innovation of counter codes, based upon two fundamental principles: first, fashion silence itself as a language of expression and second, secularize the body, consequently turning it into an object of legal rather than religious intervention. As an object of right, therefore, the body is personal. This is both, the formative concept of individual rights, as well as the stepping stone to a public life. Similarly, the practice of self-control in public life is intrinsic, both to individual character development as well as to the internal cohesion of society. However, the secularization of the body—a process that commenced with the Renaissance—never totally displaces religious and ascetic ideals but only renders their visibility much more obscure (Synott: 1992, 90-1). Thus, traditionally extolled virtues of heterosexuality, monogamy and so on, were institutionalized as ideal practices while prohibited practices were divided and re-channelized variously into domains of the law and those of the Church.

A basic modern impulse to keep public discourse sanitized and civil required proactive and constant surveillance against disruptive possibilities. The resultant vigilant character of the society was reified through incitement to discourse (Foucault: 1978)—something that is also key to understanding how meanings come to proliferate and normalize through the evolution of modernity. Essentially, not only had the society to be defended against imminent and ongoing attacks, but newer possibilities were to be apprehended and neutralized. Privation of sexuality, coupled with the essential value of its control to the health of the population, necessitated a paradoxical obligation to maintain a civilized silence around it while concurrently talking about it in as many discursive ways; this widespread proliferation of sexuality in public discourse occurs in the way of a stocktaking, as a practice in accountability and hence, the obligation to do so.5 The gaze that took stock of the body through various institutional mechanisms stripped the body of its various cultural attributes and replaced them with biological determinisms. This delocalization of the body from its cultural contingencies is precisely what secularizes it. Accordingly, sex is no longer simply an object of condemnation, but of administration and optimization. It is towards these ends that increasing policing of sex from the eighteenth century onwards is directed at, transforming it (sex) into a ‘public potential’.6 Thus, the essentialization of the public as an expressly confessional space wherein everything—tastes, opinions, practices—is considered to be a conscious avowal of what one truly is. It is also a pedagogical process as every decree and obligation to confess comes with the rider of knowing oneself, facilitating a better understanding of one’s true impulses and potential. This is therefore a society in which authority is predicated predominantly upon knowledge and predictability.

While modern, secular law becomes one of the most prominent institutions to discursive the body, the latter’s objectification and display in public discourse also occurs majorly through the discourse of medicine. Discovered as an object of medical intervention, the body is conditioned by that true scientific discourse as the boundary of individual existence; sexuality, sexual desire and pleasure become the basis of all motivation and therefore, their control and management accrue as matters of social control. In medicine, a certain power develops that is predicated upon the act of investigation, of prying open the human body and laying bare the roots of every anatomical working that simulates various unnatural pleasures (homosexuality, bestiality, necrophilia and so). The authority of medicine is owed to the existence of the body as its object, while at the same time, medicalized descriptions of human behaviour and choices increasingly gain currency in public discourse as reflections of true discourses. Consequently, morality itself, deviance, and crime are increasingly discovered as owing out of biological impulses and stimuli rather than out of the displacement of faith. Cumulatively, these practices constitute a normalizing discourse, central to which is a double impetus of pleasure and power.7 Accordingly, medicinal power derives its vitality and specific pleasures from monitoring, questioning, prying open, and having authority over the most personal of objects—the body—and its minute and obscure workings. Against this, a very different kind of pleasure emerges, one which derives not out of conformation but out of evasion of not just medicinal but various other kinds of normalizing discourses. It is important to note here that the scope for the latter kind of pleasure is determined by the points on which a certain mechanism chooses to apply itself. In essence, the normalization of heteronormativity and monogamy in modernizing discourses, has had just as much effect in expanding the scope of sexuality and sexual choices by having placed the body in the middle of a tug-of-war between pleasure and power. It is within the binding effect of this dual pull that modern subjectivity emerges. With every prohibition leading to the possibility of a concomitant evasion, modernity emerges as an optimizing discourse.

BODY AND THE GENDER DICHOTOMY

Secularization of the body is generally considered as a transformative step through which the body—otherwise a private object—is discovered both as the basis of truth, as well as a yardstick against which truth or authenticity can be measured. This discovery of the ubiquity of the body with its relationship to truth serves as the basis of society’s justification for monitoring, controlling, classifying, and managing bodies—all as matters of social security which is an obligation borne out of the social contract to constantly guard against possibilities of exposure to the state of nature. Reduction of the body as an a priori object of nature, and conflating its control with social security, conceptualizes it (body) as the very fabric of social existence; thus, the body is the first line of security against the state of nature as well as something which would invariably challenge social cohesion if not controlled and channelized. This is also how sex is transformed into a public potential, its control accruing as a matter of sustaining a certain vision of existence that is predicated upon constantly mapping the body in search of signs of truth. The matter of investigation and permissibility of margins of error in its methods derive their authority and sanction from the supreme obligation to defend the social contract. As such, these are necessary preconditions to the enjoyment of rights. The cartography of the body, however, is not an open-ended exercise; the scope of mapping the body is determined along the lines of gender binaries. Accordingly, masculinity and femininity are the basic yardsticks against which narratives of normality and abnormality or marginality are thrashed out. The stabilization of gender dichotomy as true, is caused by what could be termed as a pan-sexualization of the body,8 a process which simultaneously naturalizes the body while at the same time places it in an adversarial position vis-à-vis the progress of civilization. Reduction of the body to its sexuality on one hand, and the discovery of bodily desire at the basis of every human motivation on the other, cumulatively authorizes the secularization of the body as well as its channelization into productive categories. Gender binaries, heterosexuality, public-private dichotomy and so on, are categories that are stabilized through optimization and channelization, a process that Menon describes—in the context of law’s normalizing discourse—as violence of categories (Menon: 2007, 17). This foundational violence is constitutive of both, individual rights and the public-private dichotomy. Appropriation of women within the realm of the private and projection of the public sphere as most appropriate for the man is achieved based on perceived gender-based determinisms: male bodies, perceived as clearly bounded and solid, are considered as lending naturally to control and hence, reflecting the ideal condition of a well-guarded public space. On the other hand, women’s bodies, perceived as disorderly, penetrable, subject to cyclical changes and divisible through reproduction, challenge the very idea of a closed and controllable body surface. The resultant hierarchy between man and woman, and the superiority of the former in relation to the latter, is one upon which the public-private dichotomy is mapped. This perceived gender hierarchy is cemented not through recourse to religion but through science.9 Optimization and channelization of the sexualized body occur along the lines of avowedly scientific truths. Depiction of sexual violence as well as methods of such depictions, reinforce gender binaries while at the same time expanding the scope of discovering newer peculiarities that can either be explained along binary lines or referred to the normalizing discourses of medicine and/or the law. Censorship therefore is based on moral codes that claim to derive out of (perceived) true discourses and prohibit or permit depending upon what is perceived as normal or otherwise. The conflation of the natural, the normal, and the moral into a singular framework of interpretation are what colours the concepts of rights, consent, desire, and so. An incitement to discourse, therefore, is also an incitement to categorize whereby confession and control are authorized for the sake of ever-increasing scope for prediction, apprehension and prevention of threats to the social fabric. Additionally, categories also facilitate the channelization of the body into productive relationships with each other and the environment, a process that allows for seamless convergence between social security and capitalism.

REEL AND THE REAL

Over three decades after the film Last Tango in Paris (1972) was released and found critical acclaim all over the world as an excellent erotic drama, the lead actress in the movie, Maria Schneider revealed the real-life violation that occurred as part of making this masterpiece. The scene in question was a rape scene in which Marlon Brando uses butter as a lubricant before forcing himself onto Schneider. The actress, who died in 2011, had revealed that although she was aware of the rape scene, she wasn’t aware of the specific detail up until the part was being played out. The ‘sequence of the butter’, as it turns out, was an off-script improvisation that director Bernardo Bertolucci came up with and subsequently, took Brando into confidence about. In an interview from 2013, Bertolucci confessed that he did not update Schneider about the improvisation because he wanted the latter to ‘react as a girl, not as an actress’. And that he wanted her ‘to react humiliated’. When Bertolucci’s interview resurfaced on the internet in 2016, he reacted to the ensuing controversy by saying that it was based on a ‘ridiculous misunderstanding’.10

The decision to forego the consent of the actress portraying the condition of being raped, is based first, on a certain drive to distinguish the work as pushing the boundaries of authentic depiction and second, a well-entrenched scepticism about the capacity of professional performers—in this case, a woman—of being able to capture this projected reality in all its realistic authenticity, or at least not to the degree that the director deems as adequately authentic. In other words, the director wanted the actress to not just act but to feel raped, be raped. True to his expectations, Schneider confessed to feeling humiliated and ‘a little raped’.11 As much is also clear, Bertolucci’s justification of his decision—most importantly to himself—is expressed in his capacity as a director and the craft of his art. Consent can be foregone or taken for granted, only if in the name of authenticity in the pursuit of art. The setting in which Bertolucci’s imagination flared up, is also immensely relevant in the entire affair. According to the director, he and Brando were having breakfast one day during the shoot; and there was on the table, a baguette and butter. Of his submission, he and Brando then ‘looked at each other’ and both knew what they wanted.12 This apparent silence around what is, an act of fetish, viz., usage of butter as a lubricant, is in itself a confession of proscribed desires, its confessionary nature testified even further through the apparent, express, and ready convergence of both men’s assumptions and their mutual understanding and acknowledgement of the same. Further, the usage of butter as an external implement in the act of sex reflects a very particular tendency that equates the pan-sexualization of public space with liberation. This fetishization of sex by optimizing bodily functions through external implementation is what Foucault describes as the desexualisation of the body, an act that leads to an intensification of pleasure (Foucault: 1996, 212). An exhaustive codification of pleasure according to the laws of sex makes the latter the limit of the former. Subsequently, a ‘decoding’ or revealing of all secrets of pleasure (in terms of sex) is still widely viewed as ‘liberating’.13 This liberation through an active and participative process of experiencing, learning, and archiving the secrets of pleasure and sex, is what is largely responsible for not just pornographic depictions but also the deployment of taboo tactics such as non-consensual recording or documentation (as in the ‘sequence of the butter’), thereby simulating a pornographic trope in real life. While behind the lens it is this particularly calibrated deployment of a taboo that leads to the experience of rape; in front of the lens, the taboo is something that intensifies pleasure and liberates senses; the rape and its peculiarities, on screen, assumes a liberatory potential by uncovering a supposedly repressed truth.

There is another substratum of violence underlining it all, and something inherent in the pivot of filmmaking itself that is, the camera. Functioning as a symbol of the fourth wall in filmmaking, the camera is an offshoot of the neutral gaze of science, expressed in the perceived authenticity of the visual register itself. The construction of real life through the camera is limited only through the intentions of the one directing it. Conversely, the authority of the director ought to be understood as emanating out of the infallibility of the technology that he is wielding. In The Question Concerning Technology (1977), Heidegger points out that etymologically, the name technology stems from the Greek term technicon, which is an element of technē. Technē denotes both, activities and skills of craftsmen as well as arts of the mind and fine arts, and is linked from the earliest time, with the word epistēmē (Heidegger: 12-13). Technology, therefore, functions essentially in the field of knowledge but according to a very particular method. Technology is a mode of revealing that brings forth the truth about the form of something before its actual appearance. Modern technology too is a mode of revealing, but not in the more poetic sense as in Classical Greek narrative (Poiēsis) but in the form of a challenge to nature, of its exploitation.14 This conflation of the philosophy of knowledge through revelation, with the exploitation of nature (sexualized body as a natural object), and its subsequent deployment in the directed depiction of real life, is the primary source of acceptability and desire of not just specific forms of depiction but also of methods that guide the screening of such depictions. In Last Tango, the rape scene not only fetishizes and desexualizes the human body but clearly, the exceptionality of that sequence is highlighted even further in the context of Bertolucci’s decision to hide it from Schneider who in this scene, would be the one ‘taking it’ while Brando would be the one ‘giving/doing it’. After all, it is to accentuate Brando’s appendage that the butter is used. The assumed latency of Schneider’s role in the situation could be regarded as part reason for her being left out of the information regarding updating the script. Any assumption of the actress’ latency in the scene reflects an unquestionable conviction in the neutral gaze of the camera (and the crew) and a lacuna of appreciation of differences that underlie between a naked man and a naked woman when positioned in front of that neutral gaze of technology. This can be theorized in the context of Brando’s confession that he felt ‘humiliated’ while shooting a full frontal nude scene for the same movie when he failed to achieve a full erection on account of it being cold.15 First, it is important to note here that Brando’s self-consciousness and humiliation are despite being in front of the neutral gaze. Second, his humiliation is borne not per sé out of nudity but the inability to attain the full measure that is captured in the nude state. The essentialization of sexual vitality that is captured in this event is only further constitutive of ideal body types and capacities. Therefore, if Brando could indeed achieve a full erection—which he doubtless did in the later course of shooting—his nudity would verily serve as a signifier of power and virility in all its open glory. For a woman, to be revealing herself in front of the camera’s gaze in a candid fashion as such, is vastly different because the privation, concealment, and presentation of the woman’s body and its sexual being are readily conflated with her honour and dignity. The rule of modesty dictates that the visibility of a woman’s body is narrowly streamlined according to the purpose that is being served and the space that the body inhabits. It is precisely due to the difficulty of maintaining decreed standards of modesty in the public space that the latter is usually deemed as less conducive for a woman’s being. Consequently, the very desire of a woman to step out in the public sphere is variously considered suspect, risky, disruptive, a lack of self-control and so forth. The interoperability of rape, promiscuity, and moral turpitude in various discourses is a fact that is not particular to any culture or time.16 However, violence is not the essence of technology but a permanent capacity of it, something that is triggered as per the direction of its wielding, and according to the rules that guide its object. It is certainly pedagogical as positioning against its gaze instills as well as awakens the true feelings of one’s gender and its various natural attributes.

The 2000 movie Bawandar—depicting the 1992 gangrape and struggle of Bhanwari Devi, a women’s welfare worker affiliated with the Government of Rajasthan—directed by Jagmohan Mundhra, was fairly extolled for its candid and daring depiction of a violent and disturbing reality, while also being harshly criticized for being unnecessarily graphic and prurient in those depictions. The criticism assumed more heft when it turned out that Mundhra’s interactions with Devi had been limited to one meeting leading up to the production of the film, and that Devi had neither seen the film nor received any money from the director.17 Mundhra of course refuted these allegations with appropriate counters. While this certainly problematizes the entire process of making the film and casts it in a light of ethical suspicion, the particularities of the film itself inspire a strong suspicion regarding consultation with the rape survivor about the paradigms of the event. While the gangrape was perpetrated by Gurjars and doubtless had an obvious caste dimension to it, to even out this factor in the movie, Devi’s lawyer is depicted as being a Gurjar while in real life her lawyer was a Rajput.18 There is, politely put, scant reason to doubt that this rather sophisticated policy of a balanced portrayal of caste values, was run by Bhanwari Devi and sanctioned with the stamp of her approval. Further, in a much more stupendous blunder, a much younger actress (Nandita Das) was cast in the role of the survivor while the latter was forty years old at the time of her encounter (1992). Not enough can be said about the damage that this omission causes to the legacy of the survivors, particularly contingent experience and struggle. In his justification, Mundhra states that although inspired by Devi’s case, the film is not a biography and that certain amends are required to add drama to a film.19 He does not explain whether this requisite to add drama is one that is generic to the logic of Hindi movies, or one that is particular to the depiction of sexual and caste violence that is rampant in society and to which, people are desensitized; to the latter intention of raising awareness through cinematic depiction is robbed of its apparent progressive value if attempted without consent of the rape survivor. Notwithstanding his clarification, as much is clear that in the depiction of the event, the director prioritizes the power of his imagination over the actual event. In doing so, he decouples the gravity of the event from the event itself thereby, taking the final product as far away as possible from reality. This then is a truth that essentially hinges upon the imagination of the authority and authority of that imagination.

Films that normalize sexual violence in reinforcing gender binaries are dime-a-dozen and one is spoilt for choice. Let’s consider the movie Tum Mere Ho (1990) in which the lead roles characters are played by the-then-newcomers Aamir Khan and Juhi Chawla. The film is one of the several Nagin films, a fad that characterized Bollywood for quite a while. As such, the movie can already be reckoned as inside a ready trope. At one point in the movie, Khan’s snake charmer cum medicine man mentor explains to one of their clients (Khurana Saab) that on the night of nag panchami, it is a customary practice among his Pahari Kabila (hilly tribes) for the unmarried men to try and forcefully carry away whichever maiden they like, and if the hijack is a success, the twain are married off. He explains how this is not an easy task and that the woman aggressively tries to repel the man’s advances because, as he explains, women like to have husbands who are ‘stronger’ than them.20 Khurana Saab is then invited to stay back and see it all for himself. Khurana excuses himself from the inevitable, and on the night of nag panchami, Khan (Shiva), mock assaults Chawla (Paro), while the latter does everything that is expected of her, i.e. mock repel the attack on her mock integrity, finally being real-time carried away on Khan’s shoulders inside a small hut,21 while a cheering crowd cheers away almost gratefully. In this, the trope of rape is skilfully deployed yet casually, but in a way that manages to pass the censor board’s scrutiny, camouflages it under the garb of riwaz (custom) and a song and dance routine; this routine itself is indicative of the acceptability of the trope both within the story as well as to the viewers. Now, consider this as a prelude to the influence that later Bollywood movies probably exerted over the Indian-origin man arrested in Australia on charges of stalking. The masculine belief that access, not to consent, but to a woman’s sexuality can be obtained in ways that still do not pose an ethical problem, is sustained based on faith in the resolve of masculine desire and a deep-seated inability in a woman to repel that desire. The idea of woman as embodying nature and its various quirks—not least of which is explained away through the archaic but still floating concept of hysteria and a woman’s inability to cope with her sexuality—is something that is ancient and has evolved particularly to historical developments across time and space. As such, the relational essence of heterosexuality is essentially adversarial in which a man’s pursuit of a woman is essentially in the way of a conquest. A conquest of feminine sexuality, which does not lend itself too easily to control, is very much like nature itself and hence, has to be similarly opened up. The trope of adversity and conquest in Tum Mere Ho is much more explicit and self-explanatory in Khan’s struggles with his arch nemesis, the nagin (played by Kalpana Iyer; as per the industry norms in Bollywood, most human-snake hybrid creatures that end up bagging roles in movies happen to be females!). The mythical, mystical creature that the nagin is, can only be defeated by magic, faith, and resolve (achievable through, among other things), the snake charmer’s flute, and another conquered creature of nature, Shiva’s pet snake, Naagraj (Snake King/King of Snakes). Shiva is an alpha male who is scoring all kinds of wins against nature! Some, he wants to win (conquer), some, he has to!

Woman as a conduit of mystical powers and natural forces, and her sexuality as one of the chief sources as well as means of wielding that power, is a cumulative perception that is normalized in various discourses, from men’s rights activism to modern day witch-hunting, to explanations for romantic incompatibility. A most recent instance is the unfortunate death of budding actor Sushant Singh and the widespread public deliberation on the matter that has ensued following that event. Allegations about Singh’s girlfriend Rhea Chakraborty—of being a gold digger and a disloyal partner—scaled a new low when she was branded a witch, engaging in jaadu tona (black magic) to trap eligible men. The attack was specific in pointing out Chakraborty’s Bengali ethnicity while highlighting the fact that ‘Bengali girls are dominating’. There is just too much load to unpack over here but, the obvious fetishization of a woman’s sexuality and the dangers that would befall anyone who misjudges it turns all heterosexual pursuit into a conquest and a guilty pleasure for man. For him, a heterosexual desire is always under the shadow of a constant caveat of existential threat; the woman can be approached either by walking on eggshells or by proving the masculine mettle by taking nature (woman) on and following through to victory. Else, it is akin to riding the tigress. And thereby accrues the intensification of pleasure.

NOTES

1. ‘A Man in Australia Accused of Stalking Women Blamed it on Bollywood.’ The Washington Post (Dated 2 February 2015) . https://www.google.com/amp/s/www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2015/02/02/a-man-in-australia-accused-of-stalking-women-blamed-it-on-bollywood-his-case-was-dismissed/%3foutputType=amp

2. Ibid.

3. Ibid., p. 242.

4. Ibid., p. 243.

5. Ibid., pp. 23-4.

6. Ibid., p. 24.

7. Ibid., p. 45.

8. Commenting on the transformation of sexuality from the sixteenth century onwards, Foucault opines that sexuality henceforth, is no longer a relational concept but something that implicates the entire body. This obfuscation of sexuality as contingent and discursive, and concomitantly its projection as a universal truth, is achieved through what Foucault describes as the global organization of the desiring body. Henceforth, sexual relation is progressively displaced by the desiring body—a truth unto itself—as the site of intervention and as the basic unit of analysis. From a critical approach then, it has to be noted that sexuality’s relation to truth is not because sexuality is a gateway to truth but because the authority of truth is what grants access to sexuality. Certain mechanisms gain access to sexuality precisely based on their authority and recognition as true discourses (Foucault: 1996, 165-7).

9. Ibid., p. 30.

10. ‘Why the “Last Tango in Paris” Rape Scene is Generating Such an Outcry Now.’ The Washington Post (Dated 5 December 2016). https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/arts-and-entertainment/wp/2016/12/05/why-the-last-tango-in-paris-rape-scene-is-generating-such-an-outcry-now/?outputType=amp

11. Ibid.

12. Ibid.

13. Ibid.

14. Ibid., p. 14.

15. n. 10

16. In Jayanti Rani Panda v. State Of W.B. (1984) the Calcutta High Court passed a judgement on a rape plea brought in by a woman who was seduced into sexual intercourse on the promise of marriage but was instead abandoned by the accused when she became pregnant. The court rejected the plea because the committed act does not come within the meaning of misconception of fact; to qualify for the act to be considered as rape based on alleged misconception of fact, the promise made has to make the prosecutrix feel like she is already married (to the accused). But, it is an act of promiscuity if a ‘full-grown girl’ consents to have sex based on the promise of marriage at an unknown time in the future. The court also iterated that to qualify as a misconception of fact, the said fact has to be of immediate relevance. It is no secret that in the course of investigation of rape charges, delay in complaining is often considered as suspect grounds for promiscuity and hence, embellishment of facts. Further, the test of misconception is made even tougher with an absurd requisite of belief in already having married; in this, the law finds itself a squeezed space of not acknowledging the fact of marital rape, while at the same time reinforcing the institution of marriage as sacrosanct by terming sex outside marriage as ‘promiscuous’. But at the same time, the outrage and charge of rape brought in by the prosecutrix stems out of the ground as the law’s, i.e. the permissibility of sex only within marriage.

17. ‘Bawandar: Jagmohan Mundhra’s Film Based on Rape Victim Bhanwari Devi Runs into Controversy.’ India Today (Dated 10 December 2001). https://www.indiatoday.in/magazine/society-the-arts/story/20011210-bawandar-jagmohan-mundhras-film-based-on-rape-victim-bhanwari-devi-runs-into-controversy-774890, accessed on 10 December 2001.

18. Ibid.

19. Ibid.

20. For the sake of illustration, a few translations go as follows: ‘humare kabile ki ladkiyan apne se zyada takatvar shauhar pasand karti hai. Woh apne aap ko itna aasani se le jane nahi deti, woh pehle nochti hai, kathti hai, maarti hai, yeh kaam itna aasan nahi hai...’ (the girls of our tribe have a penchant for husbands who are stronger than them. They (girls) don’t concede so easily, first they scratch, then they bite, they hit, this is not an easy task at all...).

21. The image of the hero carrying away the heroine on his shoulders is a vision that has often been used in Hindi movies as an indicator of the strength of true love but also of a difficult situation in which consent, either of the heroine, or her family, or both, is not easily forthcoming. Consider the famous poster of the Dilwale Dulhania Le Jayenge (1995).

REFERENCES

Heidegger, Martin. 1977. The Question Concerning Technology and Other Essays. tr. William Lovitt. New York: Garland Publishing, Inc.

Foucault, Michel. 1978. The History of Sexuality, Vol. 1: An Introduction. New York: Pantheon Books.

——. 1996. Foucault Live Collected Interviews, 1961-1984, edited by Sylvère Lotringer. tr. Lysa Hocroth and John Johnston. South Pasadena: Semiotext(e).

——. 2003. Society Must Be Defended. tr. David Macey. New York: Picador.

Menon, Nivedita. 2007. Recovering Subversion: Feminist Politics beyond the Law. New Delhi: Permanent Black.

Synnott, Anthony. 1992. ‘Tomb, Temple, Machine and Self: The Social Construction of the Body.’ The British Journal Of Sociology, 43(1): 79-110.

‘A man in Australia accused of stalking women blamed it on Bollywood.’ The Washington Post (Dated 2 February 2015). https://www.google.com/amp/s/www.washingtonpost.com/news/worldviews/wp/2015/02/02/a-man-in-australia-accused-of-stalking-women-blamed-it-on-bollywood-his-case-was-dismissed/%3foutputType=amp

‘Why the “Last Tango in Paris” Rape Scene is Generating such an Outcry Now.’ The Washington Post (Dated 5 December 2016). https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/arts-and-entertainment/wp/2016/12/05/why-the-last-tango-in-paris-rape-scene-is-generating-such-an-outcry-now/?outputType=amp

‘Bawandar’, Jagmohan Mundhra’s Film Based on Rape Victim Bhanwari Devi Runs into Controversy.’ India Today (Dated 10 December 2001). https://www.indiatoday.in/magazine/society-the-arts/story/20011210-bawandar-jagmohan-mundhras-film-based-on-rape-victim-bhanwari-devi-runs-into-controversy-774890, accessed on 10 December 2001.

Judgement

Jayanti Rani Panda v. State Of W.B. [1984 Crlj 1535] (available at: https://indiankanoon.org/doc/607485/).

CHAPTER 9

Media, Social Media, and the
Gorkhaland Agitation in Darjeeling

BINU SUNDAS AND DIVYA PRADHAN

INTRODUCTION

The Gorkhaland movement has a long history. It started with the Hillmen’s Association submitting a memorandum for a ‘separate administrative set-up’ for the district of Darjeeling to the then Governor General of Bengal in 1907. Subsequently, many memoranda have been submitted for separating the Gorkha-dominated areas from the province of Bengal. Since 1907, the creation of Gorkhaland has been entrenched in the collective conscience of the people. Another memorandum, a refined version of the 1907 memorandum was again submitted to the authorities in 1917, the representative of the Darjeeling district to the Chief Secretary, Government of Bengal, demanding the ‘creation of a separate unit’. The unit in the memorandum was defined as the territory of the Darjeeling district and the Doars areas of Jalpaiguri district (Subba: 1992). Soon the declaration by the Indian National Congress in its 1920 Nagpur Session, that in post-independence India, states would be formed based on linguistic identity further fueled the imagination of Gorkhaland.

Even though the British did not separate the region from Bengal Province it did give it a special status like the Backward Track Region, etc. at different points in time. However, this did not satisfy the aspirations of the people and the demand perpetually sustained itself. After independence the Hillmen’s Association ceased to exist and the onus of sustaining the movement was spearheaded by different groups. The movement lost its momentum after Independence and only after the 1980s did it resurface in a sustained and organized form. During the 1980s when the movement was violent and widespread, it failed to capture the imagination of the ‘national mainstream media’. Media, primarily print capitalism is considered to be an important medium through which nationalism and collective identity are forged, but not until the advent of social media and 24×7 news channels did the Gorkhaland movement receive any attention from the fourth pillar of democracy. This happened because of the marginalized status of Gorkhas in the national imagination.

HISTORY OF THE MEDIA IN DARJEELING

After taking over from the Rajah of Sikkim, the British shaped and moulded Darjeeling according to their imagination. They experimented with Darjeeling and helped in developing the infrastructure of the region. From the steam engine to the Hill Cart Road, the British built everything according to their requirements. Though the British were doing things for the better administration and sustenance of their rule, it needs to be acknowledged that they were instrumental in laying the foundation for the growth in the socio-political and economic consciousness of the people.

Numerous vernacular newspapers were published in Darjeeling due to the efforts of various individuals (Subba: 1992). The precursor to these publications were the English dailies and weeklies as well as monthly journals published by the British themselves. In 1892, many newspapers were in circulation in English. The Darjeeling News and Darjeeling Standard were published weekly. On the other hand, News and Notes was a monthly journal. Towards the end of the nineteenth century, between 1897 and 1898 there was a newspaper Darjeeling-Kalimpong-Sikkim News covering a wide area, and published every month (Darjeelinghistoryclub: 2020). The first monthly in the Nepali language Gorkha Bharat Jiwan was published in 1886 from Banaras and was edited by Motiram Bhatta (Subba: 1992). From the time Gorkha Bharat Jiwan came into circulation many other dailies, weeklies and monthlies were published from Darjeeling, Kalimpong, Kurseong and Dehradun till the first decade of the 1900. Some of the prominent magazines and periodicals published when Darjeeling was under the colonial rule were Gorkhey Khabar Kagat (1901), Suktisudha (1904), Madhavi (1906), Chandra (1914), Gorkhali (1915), Janmabhumi (1922), Himalayan Times (1926), Tarun Gorkha (1928), Adarsha (1930), Nepali Sahitya Sammelan (1932), Nebula and Parivartan (1934), Goan Sudhar (1939), Gorkha Samachar (1946) (Subba: 1992). There were some like the Gorkha Sevak (1935) published in northeastern parts of India, Gorkha Samachar was published in Delhi. Himalayan Times was edited by Saheb Narendrabikram and was in English. Adarsha a monthly periodical was the only one published in Nepali that discussed the financial situation and the economic activities of the people of Darjeeling Hills (Darjeelinghistoryclub: 2020). However, some of these had to be taken out of circulation due to many factors and one such factor was the lack of a sizeable readership and the other was the lack of entrepeneurship on the part of the editors to sell their products. The spread of the Nepali diaspora warranted the need for newspapers to shed light on the socio-economic and political conditions of the Nepali population hence there were numerous print media in circulation. However, the absence of a sizeable readership forced many of these periodicals to stop publication as it was not financially sustainable.

After independence there were few other newspapers and periodicals that emerged in Darjeeling and Kalimpong districts. Some of the prominent among them were the Himalayan Observer, The Swatantra Manchko Bulletin, Abo, Himali Bela, Gorkha, Ganthi Kura Dristikon and Himalchuli. Himalchuli was the only one which was still in circulation when the Gorkhaland agitation started in the 1980s. The writers in these papers and especially in Aba played a significant role in politically mobilizing the masses the beginning of the agitation in the 1980s (Subba: 1992). There was a paradigm shift in the writings of the early 1900s to the beginning of the mobilization for Gorkhaland agitation. These writings, however, did contribute in a latent manner in constructing the collective consciousness of the people converting them into a collectivity rather than just a joining together of discrete individuals without any common denominator. The writings which emerged after this period were more politically assertive and not as defensive as the earlier ones. The political imagination of the people by this time was already established due to the politics of Akhil Bharatiya Gorkha League (ABGL) and the pan-India Nepali Bhasa Andolan.1 The latter had especially contributed immensely to the forging of a strong collective consciousness of the Gorkha population. The freshly developed collective identity made people aware of the political, social and cultural capital they possessed and provided a sense of ownership of history, geography and their location within it. The collective strength gave them the belief that they could challenge all the wrong notions most of Indian people and the government had about Gorkha history and existence. The writings started questioning their being labelled as foreigners and by implication their citizenship. This was and still is one of the most important reasons for the demand for the creation of a separate state of Gorkhaland.

MEDIA AND SOCIAL MOVEMENT IN
DARJEELING REGION

As mentioned above the demand for separation from Bengal started in 1907. The political situation of Darjeeling then and when the movement erupted again in the 1980s under the leadership of the Gorkha National Liberation Front (GNLF) was completely different. However, the only thing that was common during these two historical periods was the conspicuous absence of the media. Media is a very essential component in social movement as it helps in propagating the issues, legitimizing the claims made by the movement and more importantly it helps in shaping the public perception and understanding of the political necessity of the movement (Rohlinger & Vaccaro: 2013). Though media plays an important role in social and political movements, it did not contribute anything to propagating the issues of the Gorkhaland movement at the national level.

By the time the movement started in the 1980s only the vernacular media was present. The absence of national dailies was visible. The only national daily that was in circulation was The Telegraph and it would not reach the people on time. At the earliest, it would reach the place only in the evening. It was more or less the same with The Statesman. The other national newspapers had negligible presence in the region. The above mentioned two newspapers that were in circulation among Gorkhas were not interested in disseminating the facts of the agitation, as the government had a firm grip on the news it was printing. Radio was another medium to reach people but being part of the governmental structure it did not play any significant role in disseminating and propagating the ideology of the movement. Moreover, radio was also not a commodity that was owned by the entire population which further restricted its efficacy. Even in post-independent India, media in Darjeeling was at its nebulous stage. It could not boast of a newspaper. The media had not yet found a location of its own in the lifeworld of the people. Media was still a component of the high culture and had not yet been part of the mass popular culture. In such a situation the only medium to disseminate and circulate information and news was the bhitta or the wall.

Every place had a designated bhitta for disseminating all kinds of news to the people. For the common people the bhitta for a long time had been a site for collective participation in the political discourse. Bhitta was the site for not just participation but also for dissent and protest and a medium for articulating one's political ideology and activism. People from all walks of life gathered to read the posters as well as dictates of political parties regarding what they thought of a particular development as well as their future course of action and the role the civil society and the community had to play. Standing in front of the bhitta and reading had been part of the everyday ritual for the reticent as well as the vocal political participant. People reading the news/announcement pasted in the bhitta would relay it to people in their locality and in this manner, the news spread far and wide. Bhitta was and is part of the cultural as well as political capital of the Gorkhas demand for Gorkhaland for over a century. Mainstream media in all its forms did not have a role to play during the Gorkhaland movement in the 1980s. The media was neither functional nor dysfunctional for the activists as well as the government. However, things were to change drastically when the movement started again in the new millennium.

Society and Change in Darjeeling

During the agitation, many lives were lost and property worth crores of rupees was damaged. It is believed that approximately 1,200 lives were lost from 1986 to 1988 when the agitation was at its peak. Atrocities and violence were inflicted by the state and central police forces among the people without any discrimination based on age or gender. The agitation came to an end when the Central Government, State Government and the GNLF came into an agreement and signed the tripartite agreement for the creation of Darjeeling Gorkha Hill Council, a semi-autonomous body. However, one of the clauses in the agreement mentions that the agreement is the final settlement with regard to the demand of Gorkhaland, thereby putting an end to the aspiration of the people. This understanding created an ecosystem of animosity and the trust and support that GNLF enjoyed was gradually on the decline. GNLF was in power for almost three decades and in 2007 a reality show on television changed the political course of the region and the people.

The political dominance of the GNLF was challenged by one of its leaders, Bimal Gurung. He was able to garner the support of the people and it was very easy for him to gain the confidence of the people. GNLF had created a reign of terror and the demographic profile of the population had also undergone transformations. The young people who had witnessed the demand for Gorkhaland had internalized the importance of collective identity. In 2007 ‘Indian Idol’, the reality show became instrumental in bringing the Gorkha population spread across India as well as abroad in support of a Gorkha contestant in the show thus highlighting the collective strength of the Gorkhas. Solidarity among the people was once again at the forefront. Soon GNLF was overthrown by Gorkha Janmukti Morcha (GJM).

The GJM vehemently opposed the GNLF efforts to include the Darjeeling region under the Sixth Schedule until and unless the entire Gorkha community was included in the Scheduled Tribe list of India. The population in the hills has undergone not just quantitative but also qualitative change. The educational as well as economic status of the people had improved. The population had increased from 16.09 lakhs in 2001 to 18.47 lakhs in 2011 and the literacy rate had improved from 71.79 in 2001 to 79.56 in 2011 (Darjiling (Darjeeling) District Population Census 2011-2021-2023, West Bengal Literacy Sex Ratio and Density, n.d.). This population also had access to the media that had developed leaps and bounds since the 1980s.

The GJM was more fortunate than the GNLF as far as access to media was concerned. The prominent sources of media during the GJM-led agitation was Himalaya Darpan a local daily in Nepali published from Siliguri, the darjeelingtimes.com, and many cable television channels like the Hamro Channel, Himali Channel and Darjeeling Television. All these media outlets helped in the cause of GJM. Except Himalaya Darpan the proprietorship of the rest belonged to the natives of Darjeeling, Himalaya Darpan to establish itself took the cause of Gorkhaland and helped GJM in propagating their stories and news. GJM thus became successful in changing the narrative of the politics of the hills and once again the agitation for Gorkhaland erupted and again a tripartite agreement was signed for the creation of Gorkhaland Territorial Administration (GTA). Two differences emerged in the two agreements signed. First, it was the word Gorkhaland and second, the agreement on GTA acknowledges that the movement for Gorkhaland would sustain and carry on. With regard to polity, a very significant distinction emerged. GNLF and its leader, the Chairperson of the DGHC was seen as a puppet in the hands of the Government of West Bengal while GJM and its leader the Chief Executive Officer of GTA were cordial but was seen as indifferent of the State Government control. Bimal Gurung even led the masses when the Government did not fulfil its responsibilities towards the GTA. The media was supportive of his politics and assisted in taking his grievances against the government to the people thus making his ideas and narratives the dominant political discourse. These cable television networks had become so prominent in facilitating the connection and bonding between the people and the GJM that the District Magistrate, Darjeeling banned the telecast of cable television from 8 August to 11 August 2013, invoking the provisions of the Cable Television (Regulation) Amendment Act, 2011 (Dural: 2015).

The society in Darjeeling was witnessing rapid changes. The educational and economic status of the people were improving and many were now migrating to other places in search of better livelihood opportunities and to pursue educational aspirations. The migrant population later played a preemptive role in the movement.

Gorkhaland Movement in 2017

The relationship between the state government and the GTA was not stable and cordial, there were allegations and counter-allegations made by both parties. The GTA accused the state government of withholding transfer of departments that were listed in the agreement for the development of the region while the state government accused the GTA of embezzlement of development funds. Further, the GTA was not happy with the government for setting up Development Boards on the basis of community which they thought interfered with the functioning of the GTA. The political situation in the hills reflected the low point of the relationship between the two institutional actors, both manifesting their indignation against each other.

Particularly, the situation for the GJM, who was in power, was stable as the people were dissatisfied with the achievements and the state government was constantly accusing them of corruption and using it as a threat to discontinue the agreement. Under such a situation the West Bengal Government undertook the policy of implementing Bengal language in all the schools of the state. This was unacceptable to the people of Darjeeling and this policy implementation was perceived as language imperialism. Civil society and GJM were against the implementation of the Bengali language in place of the Nepali language. There was a protest not just from GJM but by all the Gorkha population living inside and outside of Darjeeling against this policy. Soon this gave way to the demand of Gorkhaland as it was thought that only the creation of Gorkhaland would put an end to the suppression and oppression experienced by the Gorkha people of India. During this phase of the movement, it was not just confined to Darjeeling hills alone but the demand for the creation of Gorkhaland was raised from many parts of the country.

The hills were closed for 107 days. There were hardships and troubles but the people were relentless in sustaining the bandh. Calls for the bandh to be withdrawn were made by the state and the central governments but it fell on deaf ears. The atrocities of the state became severe with every passing day. In no time 11 people were killed by the state apparatus. All the leaders of GJM were forced to go underground and it was common people who sustained the movement. The national media was mute to the happenings in the hills as usual. Only Republic Bharat reached Darjeeling to report the atrocities that people were facing. The Telegraph soon became the mouthpiece of the state government which was followed by the local vernacular Himalaya Darpan. These newspapers were printing only the government version of the story. Depending on the ideology of the owner’s television channels broadcasted news accordingly, either in favour or opposed to the state. News which till then had been more or less unbiased and objective now tended to be determined by political ideology. News became more of a propaganda tool for the government and the political order. Reality soon became what the news channels constructed to be and flooded the screen. All ideologies in the political spectrum started using television and news channels and only representational culture was given space in the news. News anchors gradually became agents of the representational culture denying space to alternative thoughts and dissenting voices.

Media and its Role During the Agitation

The agitation in 2017 was very different than the earlier ones. The leader of GJM, Bimal Gurung proclaimed in 2014 that henceforth all agitation will be peaceful according to the principles of Gandhi. The agitation in 2017 was also peaceful and the mode of dissent was to go on a strike, public rallies, street corner speeches and sloganeering. These actions were an endeavour to build the movement and the morale of all actors and also to communicate with them (Piven: 2008). However, the state apparatus was on the offensive and started using both the allocative and authoritative resources to show their power and to end the agitation. False cases were filed against all the leaders and the prominent associates of the leaders. Most of these people had more than 100 cases against them and many of them were also charged with the draconian Unlawful Activities Prevention Act. Such a situation forced all the leaders and their subordinates to hide leaving the onus of spearheading the movement to the lower cadres and the common people. The strike was sustained for 107 days till two leaders betrayed the movement and the people and forcefully withdrew the strike. There was no supply of necessary everyday requirements. People had to face tremendous hardship. Under these circumstances, there were few media which covered what was happening in the region but it soon faded out.

With the use of force and atrocities, the state was able to suppress everything and maintain its dominance in the region. The state censored all the news and the media fraternity could not get or report the actual happenings from the hills. Getting the word out on important news events from the region was such a challenge those days. In addition, countering distorted, biased and unverified news and narratives spewed by mainstream media and even social media platforms paid for by the state was almost impossible due to the lack of internet (The Centre for Internet and Society, n.d.). The hills were experiencing an existential crisis more than a political crisis as the tea gardens were closed and all form of communication was restricted by the state. The state could have acted in a humanitarian manner and showed its largess by allowing ration and other commodities to reach the people but it did not do so. The crisis in the region was much deeper than it could meet the eyes. Even in such a dire situation the media was propagating for the state and prophesizing the benefits the Chief Minister could accrue from the situation rather than reporting on the plight of the people. The Scroll wrote, ‘The agitation in West Bengal’s hill areas may end up benefitting the chief minister politically’ (Daniyal: 2017). The government used the media as an instrument to polarize public opinion. The media played its role as an instrument at the hands of the government by manufacturing false news those were detrimental to the movement. The agitation in 2017 was coordinated by the Gorkhaland Movement Coordination Committee (GMCC) comprising members from all the parties but one of the media based on the opinion of a government official reported, ‘It is clear from the decisions taken during the all-party meeting in the hills that the Morcha leadership has started compromising with the demands of other hill parties. This is a clear hint that the Morcha leadership is weakening’ (Scoopwhoop: 2017).

Social Media and the Gorkhaland Agitation

The setting in of the vernacular marked a new beginning in terms of the dissemination of opinions and news. It offered a new platform for many to understand, articulate, reflect and reflect on the political economy of the region and to an extent of those nearby places dominated by the Gorkha population. It also assisted in forging a relation among the imagined community giving a new but desired traction to the common cause of identity and the predominant politics associated with it. Furthermore, the dailies also led to the beginning of modernity and the establishment of a community, that connected by sharing their concerns and opinions about the urgent issues of the community. The dailies also helped in bringing modern technology and technological developments closure to the people. Soon technology became common which further pushed the community into a new direction of modernity and information. By the time the 2017 agitation started internet became a source of all development social, political and economic (Navarria: 2019). Internet in the guise of social media filled the vacuum that a biased and prejudiced or passive media had left.

Social media platforms like Facebook, Twitter, WhatsApp, and Instagram were all proactively used by the people to talk and write about the movement as well as the police atrocities. The activism of the people through these platforms helped in galvanizing support from those who were not in Darjeeling. The Telegraph reported on this aspect of the movement and the government was quick to ban the internet. In the absence of the Internet, it was difficult for the movement activists to synchronize and execute their plans. The use of social media helped the common people to organize themselves and connect (Lopes: 2014) and establish a pro-movement narrative. ‘The possibility to access, recombine and distribute knowledge freely or with minimum restriction can help subvert established hegemonic power positions by providing new entry points to the political process for those actors usually relegated in a non-active position by the predominant influence of existing power-holders over mainstream media networks’ (Navarria: 2019).

The use of social media helped the movement in taking the ground realities to people across the globe. With the help of social media, the movement gained momentum and protests and demonstrations were held not just in Darjeeling and other places in the country but across different countries where even a handful of people from Darjeeling were residing. There was coordination among activists from different places and also from other countries which helped in ‘gaining regional and global resonance in diverse audiences across the world’ (Porta & Mattoni: 2015, 53).

Another very important dimension of the movement was the use of WhatsApp. WhatsApp helped the activists to construct for themselves an autonomous communication, which very essential for the movement to relate with the society (Castells: 2015). This platform was used by the activists as well as the leaders to connect and to discuss and propose ideas that were important for the movement in which the main actors were missing from the scene. The multiple features of WhatsApp like voice messages and the facility to use languages other than English also helped greatly as all activists were not well versed in the English language. The voice message facility was used to the fullest. The leaders would also use this to pass on the messages in tones that were effective in arousing the sensibilities of the activists towards the movement. The activists in turn would forward these messages to the general public. The act of forwarding the messages would ensure that the message would reach the entire population. WhatsApp was very instrumental as well as successful as a medium to sustain the connection between the leaders, the activists and the general population.

The leaders who had betrayed the movement and the people had by coercion and use of state repressive apparatus usurped power and were in control of the GTA. The movement activists were hounded by the state and the police. In such a situation the general election of 2019 was pertinent to show the support that the movement and GJM enjoyed from the people. Along with WhatsApp, it was also Google Meet that played a very significant role in planning and executing the plans. According to the Secretary and President of GJM if it had not been for Google Meet and WhatsApp it would not have been possible for them to organize participation in the election. The candidate was discussed over Google Meet and WhatsApp and approval from all the stakeholders was sought. There were over 100 meetings with the use of Google Meet among party cadres hiding at different locations. The candidate for the election was also decided using these platforms. The significance of WhatsApp can be analysed from the fact that according to one of the parties functionaries, the candidate was decided at around two at night in consultation with the alliance party. All the members of the party were informed through WhatsApp immediately but by six in the morning, the candidate had to be changed as the cadres had disapproved of the candidate who was again replaced by another candidate.

Apart from the core party members making use of these platforms, they also used these platforms to generate support for the issue of Gorkhaland. Numerous Facebook pages like the Darjeeling Chronicles and Gorkhaland Flag Campaign started functioning as the spokesperson of the movement. Pro-movement information and activities in any form started being shared on these pages. The ordinary citizens who were witnessing the making of history were using their mobile phones to record (Castells: 2015). Everybody with a smartphone participating in the movement thus inadvertently became a broadcaster (Porta & Mattoni: 2015) of events which was of interest and importance for the movement and could transfer to these pages for the consumption of wider audiences. They also ridiculed the leaders who had betrayed the movement and went against the ruling party in West Bengal. These Facebook pages were instrumental in communicating with the masses and disseminating and propagating the importance of Gorkhaland and the agitation for preserving the distinct identity and cultural heritage of the region and community. They became an effective tool and the government reacted to their influence and impact by filing many false cases against them to the extent that one of the editors of Darjeeling Chronicles could not even attend his father’s funeral. Internet in the hills during the 2017 agitation and after became a medium which assisted the public and activists alike to organize and execute their everyday interactions (Fuchs: 2015) ‘in ways beyond the control of the state’ (Salem: 2015, 172).

Apart from acting in a repressive manner the government and its agencies also was proactive in surveillance. The police and other state machinery had completely overtaken the public spaces and had established their grip with the help of those who had betrayed the movement. The government tried to change the political discourse and the dominant narrative with repression at the earlier stage of the movement and when this did not have the desired effect, they tried to counter the narrative with the help of social media. The government in this endeavour was assisted by those who had joined hands with the leaders who had betrayed the movement and those who were against GJM. They also started using Facebook pages to propagate misinformation about the movement particularly about the GJM and Bimal Gurung. They would run an online voting campaign and the results would always be the candidate of the opposition winning the online voting. Along with these tactics, the agency hired by the ruling party of West Bengal to strategize their election campaign offered monetary and other benefits to the platforms that were pro-Gorkhaland. The government tried to use its agents to polarize the population through the use of these platforms and establish a narrative which showed that they were good and the movement actors were bad (Lukito et al.: 2022).

CONCLUSION

The Gorkhaland movement can be traced to 1907 when for the first time a memorandum to the then Viceroy of Bengal Presidency was submitted. Since then, the separation from Bengal has been sought after by the people of the Darjeeling region. However, this separation has still not been achieved even after more than 115 years. It is well known that media plays an important role in social movements as these movements try to ‘communicate their grievances’ and ‘build the movement and its morale’ (Piven: 2008, 23) and also communicate with the larger public. In the case of the Gorkhaland agitation due to its long history, different forms of media have come into being and the direction in which the movement has been reflected is not uniform. In the initial period, the media and the writings on it were more subdued and apologetic. In the 1980s the media became more offensive and aggressive while vehemently defending the demand and rubbishing the foreigner tag that was labelled against the Gorkha population. But this was only in the vernacular press and did not contribute much to change the perception and narrative that was dominant at the national level.

In the new millennium when the entire world was experiencing a boom in information technology, Darjeeling was readying itself to embrace this social change. There was socio-economic improvement in the people taking place and many had also socialized to this new way of life. In 2007 when the agitation again started internet became the tool for manifesting the grievances that lay dormant for years under the rule of GNLF. After a hiatus of another decade when the agitation started in 2017 the use of the internet was at the core of the movement. The press and television were to a large extent under the control of the government. Therefore, social media was the only resource in the hands of the people to fight the repression and atrocities of the state and its apparatuses collectively. Any form of physical gathering or collectivity was not possible due to the brutality of the state. Social media helped people to collectively raise pertinent issues and make one another aware of what the state was doing. Internet and social media have provided an alternative to mobilization and have provided a platform where individuals can perform different roles. They can manifest their power by breaking rules and interacting with many other like-minded actors. Social media provided a space where people could exercise their agency not just individually but also collectively without being identified by the authorities and making them victims of their brutality. Social media empowered common people in their fight against the state by providing them an identity of anonymity.

Anonymity gave people the courage to act against the combination of all state actors along with the leaders who had betrayed the movement and their team but at the same time, it did not all the time facilitate sameness and oneness of activities carried by different individuals. This anonymity also acted as an impediment towards the movement as many opposed to the movement and the leadership using the internet and social media also propagated—anti-movement narratives. However, Darjeeling being a small region and with not so big population it was not very difficult for the state to at least roughly identify the users as they controlled to internet service providers. On the one hand, the nexus between the corporates and the state became detrimental to achieving effective results on the other social media has provided a viable space for non-state actors to challenge the dominance and hegemony of the state (Trottier & Fuchs: 2015).

Darjeeling during the agitation witnessed an increase in the use of social media. GJM was successful in using it to fulfil its political objective by mobilizing people and passing its message across the people. This helped the people to realize the potential power of collective identity and solidarity. As a consequence, they were able to win election in the 2019 general elections and prove that the people were in support of their demand for Gorkhaland. Most importantly the use of social media was instrumental in raising sensibilities towards the movement and one another. From being defensive in the media in the earlier phase to actively partial writings in the 1980s, the use of social media in the agitation of 2017 and after, helped the leaders and most importantly, the majority of the people to be legally, constitutionally and socially erudite and fight the state in their just and rightful demand of separation from the state of West Bengal.

NOTE

1. Nepali Bhasa Andolan was the agitation for the inclusion of Nepali Language in the Eighth Schedule of the Indian Constitution thereby granting it a recognition as one of the Indian languages.

REFERENCES

Bengal Govt Sees Signs of Weakness in Gorkhaland Movement, Not Withdrawing Central Forces (21 June 2017). ScoopWhoop. https://www.scoopwhoop.com/news/bengal-govt-sees-signs-of-weakness-in-gorkhaland-movement-not-withdrawing-central-forces/

Castells, M. (2015). Networks of Outrage and Hope: Social Movements in the Internet Age (Second). Polity Press.

Daniyal, S. (21 June 2017). Identity Politics: Gorkhaland is to Mamata what Kashmir is to Modi [Text]. Scroll. In; https://scroll.in. https://scroll.in/article/841225/identity-politics-gorkhaland-is-to-mamata-what-kashmir-is-to-modi

Darjeelinghistoryclub (20 July 2020). ‘Newspaper Publications in Colonial Darjeeling Hills’. Darjeeling History Club. https://darjeelinghistoryclub.wordpress.com/2020/07/20/newspaper-publications-in-colonial-darjeeling-hills/

Darjiling (Darjeeling) District Population Census 2011–2021–2023, West Bengal Literacy Sex Ratio and Density (n.d.). Accessed on 25 September 2023, from https://www.census2011.co.in/census/district/1-darjiling.html

Dural, R. (2015). Media and Politics: An Exploration of the Role of Media in Political Movements in the Context of Darjeeling Hills in West Bengal. http://ir.nbu.ac.in/handle/123456789/3751

Fuchs, C. (2015). ‘Anonymous: Hacktivism and Contemporary Politics’. In Social Media, Politics and the State: Protests, Revolutions, Riots, Crime and Policing in the Age of Facebook, Twitter and YouTube, edited by Daniela Trottier and Christian Fuchs, Routledge: 88-106.

Lopes, A.R. (2014). The Impact of Social Media on Social Movements: The New Opportunity and Mobilizing Structure. Accessed on 25 September 2023, from https://www.creighton.edu/fileadmin/user/CCAS/departments/PoliticalScience/Journal_of_Political_Research__JPR_/2014_JSP_papers/Lopes_JPR.pdf

Lukito, J., Cui, Z., Hu, A., Lee, T., and Ozawa, J.V.S. (2022). ‘States vs. Social Movements: Protests and State Repression in Asia’. Media and Communication, 10(4): 5-17. https://doi.org/10.17645/mac.v10i4.5623.

Navarria, Giovanni (2019). The Networked Citizen: Power, Politics and Resistance in the Internet Age. Palgrave Macmillan.

Piven, F.F. (2008). Challenging Authority: How Ordinary People Change America. Rowman & Littlefield Publishers.

Porta, D. Della and Mattoni, A. (2015). ‘Social Networking Sites in Pro-democracy and Anti-austerity Protests: Some Thoughts from a Social Movement Perspective’. In Social Media, Politics and the State: Protests, Revolutions, Riots, Crime and Policing in the Age of Facebook, Twitter and YouTube, edited by Daniela Trottier and Christian Fuchs, Routledge: 39-63.

Rohlinger, D. and Vaccaro, C. (2013). ‘Media and Social Movements’. In The Wiley-Blackwell Encyclopedia of Social and Political Movements. John Wiley & Sons, Ltd. https://doi.org/10.1002/9780470674871.wbespm128

Salem, S. (2015). ‘Creating Spaces for Dissent: The Role of Social Media in the 2011 Egyptian Revolution’. In Social Media, Politics and the State: Protests, Revolutions, Riots, Crime and Policing in the Age of Facebook, Twitter and You Tube, edited by Daniela Trottier and Christian Fuchs, Routledge, 171-88.

Subba, T.B. (1992). Ethnicity, State, and Development: A Case Study of the Gorkhaland Movement in Darjeeling. Har-Anand Publications.

Trottier, D. and Fuchs, C. (2015). ‘Theorizing Social Media, Politics and the State: An Intoduction’. In Social Media, Politics and the State: Protests, Revolutions, Riots, Crime and Policing in the Age of Facebook, Twitter and YouTube, edited by Daniela Trottier and Christian Fuchs, Routledge, 3-38.